in light of prostate cancer awareness
month I'd like to introduce you to John
a 43-year-old male who believed he
epitomized Health he set an hour aside
daily to exercise stayed away from fast
foods and he was the first person
friends and family thought of whenever
they had health concerns despite not
visiting a doctor since his early 30s he
was suddenly thrown into turmoil when he
started experiencing pelvic pain and
urinary changes to urinary habits a
visit to the doctor revealed a 1.5 mm
Mass which was later diagnosed as
prostate cancer the weight of this news
you can imagine really hit John he
grappled with Marriot emotions
questioning his very identity as a
healthy individual despite family
history of the disease and leading a
seemingly healthy lifestyle with regular
exercise a balanced diet John was
perplexed by this diagnosis with
responsibilities as a father as the
primary caregiver of his parents his
diagnosis turned his world upside down
you can imagine upside down plagued with
anxiety and sinking into depression
John sought answers he delved deep
trying to pinpoint any lifestyle choices
that could have precipitated this
frightening disease he was confident it
was not his nutrition but imagine if the
very Foods you or the men in your family
consider
nutritious are silently eroding of their
prostate health today on true Health
Tuesdays we will unravel some myths
about dietary habits exposing Foods
adversely affecting prostate health
number one
Dairy despite the nutritional value
Dairy is loaded with exogenous sources
of hormones growth hormones estrogen
progesterone and these hormones
unfortunately affect hormone sensitive
tumors men who consume Dairy face a 30%
increased risk for prostate cancer
however there's hope almond milk a dairy
alternative can suppress prostate cancer
progression by
30% number two
eggs a staple for many especially gy
Enthusiast like John eggs can be
detrimental for prostate health men who
consume
2 and a half eggs or more per week have
an
81% chance of lethal prostate cancer the
culprit Chine Coline is a driver
prostate cancer so you should avoid eggs
number three red and processed Meats
from bacon to hot dogs when you fry
these dead animals they release a
chemical called heterocyclic amines
they're known
carcinogens that have the ability to
mutate our DNA any alterations in DNA
can be a driver to cancer and in this
case prostate cancer moreover men
consuming chicken and turkey face up to
four times the risk of prostate cancer
progression so men be sure to take a
look at your meat if you have any
prostate concerns review the meat
products you're consuming they just
might be dry driving your prostate
health issues number four fried fish a
fish diet can be a bit tricky men who
frequently indulge in fried fish double
their risk of prostate cancer many fish
are contaminated with dioxins and BPA
and Bates microplastics and heavy metals
and a lot of the environmental toxicants
that are in fish are fatty in nature
they're fat Sol able they store in fat
tissue and they have the ability to
influence our endocrine system they're
known as endocrine disrupting
chemicals and for that reason if you
have a prostate issue you have to avoid
any exogenous sources of these chemicals
that can act as hormones and affect our
hormonal signals in our system number
five french fries and
donuts tasty as they might be frequent
consumption of these deep fried treats
increases the risk of prostate cancer by
37% John's love for French
fries unknowingly contributed to his
prostate health
concerns number six alcohol while
occasional
Indulgence might seem harmless men
consuming three or more drinks per week
double the risk of advanced prostate
cancer so men be sure to avoid alcohol
being informed is the first step to
making healthier choices John's journey
is a stark reminder of the importance of
regular checkups and understanding the
nuances of dietary
habits this Prostate Cancer Awareness
Month let's prioritize our health and
make informed
choices